After discussing the bounded buffer
producer/consumer problem, let's
move to resource allocation.
We are going to make a small,
yet important change to our problem definition.
In this new model, threads need to acquire
multiple resources to complete a task.
The new pseudocode for the
model is shown in the slide.
We still want to ensure mutual
exclusion, progress, and fairness.
Pay attention to 2 aspects, though:
First, each thread needs to acquire
all the resources it needs to
proceed, not just part of them.
Second, to ensure progress we need to ensure
threads cannot enter a deadlock state.
So, what is a deadlock?
A set of processes/threads blocking each
other so that none of them can proceed.
Can we have some formal reasoning about what
could cause a deadlock? Luckily yes. Coffman,
back in 1971, proved that for a deadlock
to happen, all the following conditions
need to hold simultaneously:
mutual exclusion is enforced.
A process or thread that already holds one
resource can ask for a second resource and
wait for it without releasing the resource it
already holds (this is called hold and wait)
There is no preemption: a resource can only be
released by the process/thread that holds it
and there is a circular wait: a circular
chain of 2 or more blocked processes/threads
each waiting for a resource held by
the next process/thread in the chain
Knowing that these 4 conditions need
to hold simultaneously implies that by
removing one of them, then we can prevent
deadlocks. Of course, we cannot remove the
mutual exclusion, ensuring it is our goal,
but we can eliminate one of the other 3.
We can eliminate the circular wait by making sure
that resources are acquired in a certain order.
We can eliminate the non-preemption,
by having a thread releasing a resource
if it cannot get the next one.
Or, we can eliminate the hold and wait,
making sure a thread either gets all
its resources at once or none of it.